A Guide to the John D. Rockefeller papers FA002
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Correspondence, C; 34.4 cubic ft. 86 boxes
  - Business Investments, I; 6.0 cubic ft. 15 boxes
    - Wabash Railroad Company - Wetmore, 124.0 pages (Box 86, Folder 639, Reel 10, Frame 0629)
      Wabash Railroad Company, 1891-1893. New York, New York. Notice of meetings; proxies. Wadsworth, J., 1/16/1885. New York, New York. Call on Chicago, Milwaukee & St. Paul Railway Company bonds. Wade Park Banking Company, undated. Cleveland, Ohio. Announcement of new bank, with Frank Rockefeller as president. Wagner Palace Car Company, 1888, 1890-1891. New York, New York. Stock split; dividends. Walker, J. E., 9/17/1890. Moline, Illinois. Plan for building and loan association. Walker Manufacturing Company, 1890. Cleveland, Ohio. Bonds prospectus. Waller, J. L. & Company, 1893. Chicago, Illinois. Offer real estate in Wisconsin. Walsh, T. H., 2/12/1891. Montreal, Canada. Inventor of train coupling device seeks capital to develop patents. Walter, G. B., 5/17/1887. New York, New York. Offers timberlands in Tennessee. Warden, W. G., 12/4/1890. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Standard Oil Company official introduces Governor E. E. Jackson of Maryland. Wardwell, W. T., 1893. New York, New York. Standard Oil Company of New York; loans to John D. Rockefeller handled through Jesup & Lamont; money markets. Waring, O. T., 1885. New York, New York. Standard Oil Trust official; purchase of office supplies; arrangement of telegraph lines. Waring, R. S., 1885-1888. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Underground cable investment; Waring Cable Company; Standard Underground Cable Company. Warmington, G. H., 1893. Cleveland, Ohio. People's Gas Light Company investment offer. Warner, I. E., 8/11/1893. Baltimore, Maryland. Pure Rubber Paint Company; seeks capital. Warren, F. T., 10/1/1891. San Francisco, California. Offers timberland on Pacific Coast. Warren, T., 4/3/1891. St. Louis, Missouri. Banking opportunity in St. Louis. Washington Trust Company, 1890-1893. New York, New York. Announcements; dividends. Waterbury, Mrs. M. A., 1888-1890. Chicago, Illinois. Deposited $1,000 with John D. Rockefeller. Waterhouse, D., 1/28/1890. Chattanooga, Tennessee. Offers real estate in Tennessee. Watkins, J. B., 1891. New York, New York. Building railroad into timber country on Gulf Coast. Watkins, W. G., 1889. New York, New York. Offers investment opportunity in South Carolina. Watkins, William, 10/14/1891. Cazenovia, New York. Seeks investment in Plaza Bank. Watkins, William H., 4/4/1893. Chicago, Illinois. Offers real estate in Chicago. Watriss, Breese & Cummings, 5/10/1890. Chicago, Illinois. Bankers and brokers. Webb, F. J., 3/29/1887. Syracuse, New York. Freeman & Webb; real estate and bond brokers; offers to investigate local gas company stock. Welling & Malcom, 1890. New York, New York. Brokers; offers securities. Wellington, S. B., 3/31/1888. New York, New York. U. S. Cement Company; plan for control of cement industry. Wellman, J. H., 6/5/1888. Boston, Massachusetts. Central Car Company; sends check for excess interest on John D. Rockefeller remittance. Wells, E. F., 9/22/1893. San Diego, California. Offers investment; San Diego & Phoenix Railroad Company. Western Exploration Company, 1891-1892. Unidentified location. Memorandum regarding stock. Western Union Telegraph Company, 3/31/1886. New York, New York. Quarterly report. Wetmore, C. W., 1889-1891. New York, New York. Barlow & Wetmore, attorneys; James B. Colgate & Company; American Steel Barge Company; Penokee & Gogebic Consolidated Mines; Puget sound Pulp & Paper Company; Southwestern Coal & Improvement Company; Northern Pacific Railroad Company; meeting announcements; stock subscriptions; loans to E. A. & J. O. Hayes.
    - Wheeler - Wright & Sons, 98.0 pages (Box 86, Folder 640, Reel 10, Frame 0753)
      Wheeler, O. H., 3/17/1890. Williamsport, Pennsylvania. Land scheme. White, S. V. & Company, undated. New York, New York. Bankers & brokers; offer bonds. Whitmore, W. R., 1892. New York, New York. Offers securities; Hall Signal Company; attempts to bribe F. T. Gates. Whitmore, W. W., 2/16/1891. New York, New York. James B. Colgate & Company; business scheme. Wick, H., 7/23/1891. Cleveland, Ohio. Henry Wick & Company, bankers; announce reorganization of firm. Wiener, A., 1888. Cleveland, Ohio. Offers timber and iron lands in Michigan. Wilcox, A. P., 7/11/1885. Austin, [Minnesota?]. Report on crops along Chicago, Milwaukee & St. Paul Railroad Company lines in South Dakota and Minnesota. Wilder, William H ., 1892. Florence, Massachusetts. Central Oilgas Stove Company; consolidation of oil stove interests. Wilkison, J. E., 1891-1893. Fostoria, Ohio. Northwestern Ohio Natural Gas; dividends. Willard, C. E., 1893. New York, New York. Interview with F. T. Gates regarding job offer at iron mines. Williams, A., 5/12/1892. Louisville, Kentucky. Offers timber, coal, and iron lands in Kentucky and Tennessee. Williams, J. T., 6/21/1888. Mt. Vernon, New York. Inventor of electrical mail transmission system. Willingham, T., 1/12/1890. Atlanta, Georgia. Securities for sale; North Alabama Furnace, Foundry & Land Company. Willis, C. A., 2/29/1892. New York, New York. Interview request. Wilson, George, 1892. New York, New York. Standard Oil Company, accountant; John D. Rockefeller accounts. Wilson, W. G., 5/23/1887. Chicago, Illinois. Sewing machine monopoly plan. Wilson & Welles, 1888-1893. New York, New York. Brokers; offer securities; description of Pocantico Water Works Company. Winans, H., 1890-1893. New York, New York. Real estate broker; offers loan and property in city, Portland, Oregon, and Omaha, Nebraska. Winthrop, R. & Company, 1890. New York, New York. Brokers; offer bonds; Utica & Black River Railroad Company. Wisconsin Central Company, 1889. Boston, Massachusetts. Interest on bonds. Wisebart, B. W., 6/27/1890. Denver, Colorado. Offers mining lands in Colorado. Wolcott, O. L., 3/4/1893. Warren, Ohio. Western Reserve National Bank; Cleveland real estate mortgage bonds. Wood, Mrs. E. H., 6/16/1891. Bellevue, Ohio. Standard Oil Trust stock purchase request for son. Wood, R. B., 6/22/1891. Bellevue, Ohio. Sends check for Standard Oil Trust certificate. Wood, T. J., 9/14/1893. Crown Point, Indiana. Attorney; offers phosphate, timber, and farm lands in Florida. Woodward, J. T., 1890-1893. New York, New York. Sends Hanover National Bank stock; notice of tax assessment on bank stocks; proxy. Worral, T. P., 2/29/1892. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Proposed Union Cotton Warehouse & Compress Company in Augusta, Georgia. Wright, J. H., 1885. New York, New York. Standard Oil Company of New York; John D. Rockefeller office supplies. Wright, Dunbar, 8/17/1893. New York, New York. Standard Oil Company of New York; requests advice and loan on stocks. Wright, Peter & Sons, 1888-1889. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Purchases of Inman & International Steamship Company stock; notice of call and payment on subscription; proxy.
    - Introductory Materials, 53.0 pages (Reel M 01, Folder 1)
      Register to the John D. Rockefeller, Sr., Business Investments Correspondence.
      Documents available in Boxes 72 and 73. Documents are closed to researchers.
  - Office, O; 20.0 cubic ft. 50 boxes
    The business was the heart of John D. Rockefeller's achievement and importance, but the office correspondence issued is even more extensive and more fascinating than the business material. By the latter part of the 1870s Rockefeller was a widely known figure, and the number and variety of persons who wrote to him is remarkable. They wrote for almost every imaginable reason. Mostly they cajoled, begged, and curried favor. Here we hear America singing, though hardly the songs Walt Whitman heard. Alpha the Astrologer, for example, wrote from New York City: "Successfully answers all questions pertaining to buying and selling of stocks, bonds, grain, cotton, real estate, journeys & etc. Two dollars... Highest references if required."* Requests for loans were common, often bearing some assurance like that in a letter from Benjamin Albertson, contractor and builder of Asbury Park, New Jersey: "I am not a speculator or crank of any kind." Albertson, like many of the correspondents, did not actually know Rockefeller but felt no compunction about making the most outrageous demands of him. "I will call at your Residence No 4 W 54th st on Thursday Evening the 18th inst at 8:30 P.M.," Albertson peremptorily announced, "to see if you will save me from ruin. It will not take a large amount of money, and I have Real Estate security that I can give you."**
    Sometimes those in public life felt that Mr. Rockefeller was in their debt, and they were not shy about asking for what they felt was coming to them. Paul Babcock, Jr., one of Rockefeller's business associates, wrote in 1880, for example, to find out how the Standard Oil Company wished to respond to a request from an influential Democrat in the New Jersey state legislature: "I have received a message from the Hon. Thos. H. O'Connor of Newark that he would be glad to receive his expenses incurred in the recent session... in introducing & urging his Bill against Pipe Lines in the State of New Jersey... My own judgment was & is to refuse to pay one dollar!"***
    Appeals came from the mighty as well as from the less well known. The rich were already practicing the habit of soliciting each other in support of their personal good causes. Many of those in society and in the business world contacted Mr. Rockefeller seeking donations. Andrew Carnegie, for example, wrote in 1889 seeking a gift for what would shortly emerge as Carnegie Hall: "Perhaps the effort to give New York what the Post recently said was its most pressing need may commend itself to you," the steel king opened. "Our numerous musical organizations would naturally be gratified to have your name among their supporters." And, lest the oil magnate think this some otherworldly scheme, Carnegie assured him that "the Hall will be managed... upon business principles to pay interest like any other Real Estate investment."****
    Requests for testimonials and endorsements of products were among the many demands made of Mr. Rockefeller. Fred Adee & Co., purveyors of plumbers' supplies and sole agents for Zane's patent water closet ("The Sanitary"), asked whether he would oblige with an opinion of the merits of their product, recently installed in his residence. "We are about to issue a new catalogue and desire to include in it a testimonial from you," they explained.***** Many people also wrote seeking jobs or help for their sick and dying relatives.
    Few good causes went forward without offering him the opportunity to take part. Solicitations from museums, hospitals, temperance groups, welfare organizations of every stripe and hue, and educational institutions were particularly evident. Most received standard polite but negative replies from his staff, though a great many succeeded in winning his help. Among these were some of the nation's major universities, particularly Brown and the new University of Chicago, to which Rockefeller gave millions. He exercised his influence on behalf of his favored institutions in manifold ways, as a letter from his trusted lieutenant Frederick T. Gates shows. From the Standard headquarters at 26 Broadway, Gates wrote in 1893 to Rockefeller in Cleveland:
    President E. Benjamin Andrews of Brown University called upon me yesterday explaining that his call was simply friendly without business. I knew, however, he must have some object. In the course of the conversation seeing that he was not going to unfold his errand but expected me to open up, I waited until he was ready to go, and in fact had started. I then called him back and ventured to hope that he had not given up the idea of going to Chicago with Dr. [William Rainey] Harper. He then opened up the real business for which he came. He said he was not sure whether Mr. Rockefeller personally would like to have him go or not. I told him... that Mr. Rockefeller would be distinctly gratified if he could find it in the line of his duty to go to Chicago and take hold with Dr. Harper. He seemed to have a burden lifted by the announcement. I have written very briefly to Dr. Harper and I think it now very probable that Andrews can be had.******
    By far the greatest volume of letters related to requests from those pursuing religious or moral goals, above all for Baptist causes. J. B. Cranfill, Superintendent of Missions for the Baptist General Convention of Texas, wrote repeatedly, though apparently unsuccessfully. Texas, he noted, "is a vast foreign and home mission field and the work for the Master here has paid. Our people use your 'Standard Oil' for they can't get any other kind, and I feel that you ought to give me some mission money to keep these people from getting into the oil tank of the future world. I will be satisfied with $500 and will not boycott your oil if you don't give a cent. With cordial good wishes and trusting the Lord will help you in all things, I am, Yours Fraternally, J. B. Cranfill."*******
    The pleas for contributions often received the same thorough, rational, careful evaluation that Rockefeller's staff gave to his investments. Frederick T. Gates handled much of this work, and it is interesting to compare his reports on proposed for-profit investments with his quite similar judgments about the soundness, stability, and long-run prospects of charitable supplicants. For example, Gates, in his capacity as the corresponding secretary of the American Baptist Education Society, investigated and then reported adversely on the request for a sanitarium for Baptist missionaries. He listed numerous reasons, such as the fact that "the $1,200 endows a bed not a room, which would take $15,000 it appears including treatment." In addition, "the fund goes to the sanitarium co. not as your correspondent supposes to the Missionary Union," and furthermore, "the sanitarium affords insufficient guaranties of permanency."******** Similarly, in responding to an inquiry from Rockefeller's secretary, George D. Rogers, Gates urged that a loan not be given to a milling company whose owner did business with a barge firm in which Rockefeller had an interest, ticking off a long list of reasons ranging from the fact that the collateral was not valuable to considerations that the business was "a very fluctuating one," "profits are uncertain," and "why should he [Rockefeller] be saddled with every enterprise which can possibly contribute to the Barge profits."********* All inquiries, whether seeking contributions, loans, or favors, took on added complexity when they came from someone with a business connection to Rockefeller. Gates, for example, proceeded cautiously in a matter involving a request for a Baptist charity when "the fact this gentleman is probably connected with your business... leads me to await your instructions before undertaking a thorough investigation."********** The same subtlety and care were called for on the part of others associated with Rockefeller. The secretary of the University of Chicago, for example, made an exception to his usual policy of refusing to "address you on business" by commending to Rockefeller a gentleman seeking investors in "the new process of making aluminum." The reason was that the person in question, "a man of very rare intelligence & beautiful spirit," had made a $20,000 contribution to the seminary endowment at the university and "I cannot therefore say no! to him."*********** The tangled web of connections shaped not only the personal and philanthropic correspondence, but also the materials relating to business investments, found in Subseries I.
    Glenn Porter Director Hagley Museum and Library --------------------------------------------------------- * Alpha the Astrologer to John D. Rockefeller, n.d., Family Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries O. Box 1. Folder 2. ** Albertson to John D. Rockefeller, December 17, 1890. Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries O. Box 1. Folder 2. *** Babcock to Rockefeller, April 4, 1880. Archives. RG 1.2. Series C. Subseries B. Box 52. Folder 387. **** Carnegie to Rockefeller, April 20, 1889. Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries O. Box 6. Folder 49. Rockefeller declined, saying "I am pleased that you are moving forward in the effort to secure the additional musical advantages for New York, in the construction of a proposed new building &c and regret that I am deprived from joining you, on account of having so many other undertakings on hand." Rockefeller to Carnegie, April 24, 1889. Archives. RG 1. Letterbooks. Book 019, p. 373. ***** Adee & Co., to Rockefeller, March 9, 1885. Archives. RG 1.2. Series C. Subseries O. Box 1. Folder 2. ****** Gates to Rockefeller, October 3, 1893. Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries O. Box 16. Folder 124. ******* Cranfill to Rockefeller, March 12, 1890. Archives. RG 1.2. Series C. Subseries O. Box 10. Folder 74. ******** Gates to Rockefeller, November 6, 1891. Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries O. Box 16. Folder 123. ********* Gates to Rogers, December 30, 1892. Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries O. Box 16. Folder 124. ********** Gates to Rockefeller, May 18, 1892. Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries O. Box 16. Folder 123. *********** T. W. Goodspeed to Rockefeller, October 6, 1890. Family Archives. RG 1. Series C. Subseries I. Box 72. Folder 535.
    - A Newspaper Man - Adams, Edgar, 110.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1, Frame 0303)
      Real estate; inventions; job applicants, personal loans; California College; New England Intercollegiate Press Association; Burnham Industrial Farm; Vassar College; Worcester Academy; Standard Oil Company employees; Methodist Church; history of Baptist Churches of New York State; Methodist Episcopal Church; Lima College; F. T. Gates letter on schism between Southern Baptist Home Mission Society and American Baptist Home Mission Society; student assistance; Women's Baptist Foreign Mission Society; day nursery fund subscription; Euclid Avenue Baptist Church; preparations for John D. Rockefeller Western trip.
    - Adams, Edward - Alexander, J. H., 130.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1, Frame 0413)
      Personal appeals; trust fund for American art and artists; Baptist Church appeals; farm mortgages in Kansas; Children's Hospital; anti-union newspaper, "Equity;" candidate for position of correspondence secretary of the American Baptist Missionary Union; American Baptist Home Mission Society work among the Mormons; Children's Fresh Air Fund; Carlsbad, Germany, sanitarium; New York Sabbath Committee; First Ward Industrial School.
    - Alexander, Mrs. W. H. - Allyn Brothers, 132.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1, Frame 0543)
      Women's Baptist Home Mission Society; Women's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU); University of Chicago; personal loans; student assistance; Twilight Club; investment offers; Baptist Church appeals; Reform School for boys; Brownsville Female College; appeal for missionary in China; American Baptist Missionary Union; John D. Rockefeller physical exam; New York Homeopathic Medical College and Hospital; European guide; real estate; Baptist University in North Dakota.
    - Alman, Samuel, 1882-1894; 90.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 4, Page 1, Frame 0675)
      Emannuel Baptist Church; appeals; thank-yous; F. T. Gates letter regarding New York City Baptist Mission Society; American Baptist Education Society.
    - Alpha the Astrologer - Anderson, Frankie M., 78.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1, Frame 0765)
      Investment advice; personal aid; Leeds Land & Improvement Company of Sioux City bonds; job applicants; Old Ladies Home; American Academy of Political and Social Science; American Association for the Advancement of Science; American Baptist Home Mission Society; Indian University, Indian Territory [later Bacone University]; American Congress of Churches; American Fine Arts Society; American Museum of Natural History; American Seamen's Friend Society; Baptist seminary; Monroe Female College; steamboiler company stock venture.
    - Anderson, Galusha, 1880-1893; 63.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1, Frame 0843)
      Appeals and thanks for contributions to old University of Chicago; Denison University appeals and request for interview; terms of John D. Rockefeller donation to Denison; thanks for visit at Forest Hill; John D. Rockefeller assistance to colored student at Denison; congratulation on Bessie's marriage and condolence for death of mother; thanks for hospitality.
    - Anderson, J. Y. - Arbuckle, 127.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1, Frame 0906)
      University of Rochester; job applicant; Glade Spring Academy; attorneys; German Protestant Church; Zum Schifflein Christi; Charity Organization Society; George H. Vilas testimonial; town library; Brown University; University of Chicago; Benevolent Society; Old Ladies Home; mining investment; horse shipment rates; Dewey decimal classification system; University of Michigan; St. John's Orphanage for Boys; real estate; Baptist sanitarium; Euclid Avenue Baptist Church; help poor with message; Episcopal Church.
    - Archbold, John D., 1880-1894; 53.0 pages (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1, Frame 1033)
      Weekly letters on abstinence from alcohol; comments on oil industry; Acme Oil Company of New York; contributions to New York Skin and Cancer Hospital; personal items; John D. Rockefeller memorandum on Mark Hanna letter regarding William McKinley, 1892 U. S. presidential election.
    - Arden - Arthur, 114.0 pages (Box 2, Folder 9, Reel 2, Frame 0001)
      Personal assistance; Cleveland Philharmonic Orchestra; job applicants; Irving Club; Fifth Avenue Baptist Church; personal matters; "The New Princeton Review"; religious publications for Freedmen; relatives of John D. Rockefeller; Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute; Army Aid Association; Standard Oil Company; Masonic Home; Home for Incurables; Standard Oil Trust stock purchase; New York Philharmonic club; Anti-Saloon Republican League; Art Club; Methodist Church; World's Columbian Exposition; medicinal springs; Cleveland Vocal Society.
    - Asbury - Ashworth, 47.0 pages (Box 2, Folder 10, Reel 2, Frame 0115)
      Monroe Female College; Baptist Church; Western Reserve Academy; Episcopal Church.
    - Aspell, Dodie I., 1885-1891; 87.0 pages (Reel 2, Frame 0162, Box 2, Folder 11)
      New York secretary and telegrapher; office operations; supplies; personnel matters; household matters.
    - Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor - Avery, S. S., 115.0 pages (Reel 2, Frame 0249, Box 2, Folder 12)
      Association for Improving the Condition of the Poor; Freedman School in west; copper mines in Arizona; private railroad car offer; Non-Partisan Prohibitory Amendment League; Baptist Church; Homeopathic Hospital College; student assistance; Normal and Industrial School for Girls; F. T. Gates report; New York Sabbath Committee; real estate; bronze foundry; oriental art; Pennsylvania Baptist General Association; Standard Oil Company employees; job applicants; Cleveland City Council Committee on House of Refuge; proposed City Farm School; American Association for the Advancement of Science; Chatham Square Mission, Mariners' Temple; Congregational Church; John D. Rockefeller relatives; New York Vocal Union; Relief Concert.
    - Ayer - Aspurua, 56.0 pages (Reel 2, Frame 0364, Box 2, Folder 13)
      Feller Institute of the Grande Ligne Mission; F. T. Gates report; real estate; job applicant; sewing machine invention; historical works on Latin America.
    - B - Bacon, 63.0 pages (Reel 2, Frame 0420, Box 2, Folder 14)